MAN: Previously on Gotham...
Where are you, Ed?
What's green and red
and goes round and round?
Zebra with a gaping hole.
Your brilliant mind is as
damaged as the rest of your body.
I guess she was right.
You're not smart.
We'd need an army
to take on Penguin.
Makes me miss Falcone.
SOFIA: You came looking for a
gangster, that's exactly what you found.
I'm a Falcone.
I need to know what
you're going to do.
You want the city
back from Penguin,
I'll give that to you.
Did you really think I
wouldn't figure it out?
The two of you have been
whispering like teenagers for weeks.
You never deserved
her in the first place.
Yes, I killed him.
I am sorry.
BRUCE: There's a
legend about this knife.
The man that killed my
grandfather can't have this.
I promise.
That's Ra's al Ghul.
That knife is the
key to everything.
Give me the knife and
I will release the boy.
- Bruce, hand me the knife.
- I can't.
(KNIFE SLICING)
(SCREAMS)
DRIVER: So who's the vegetable?
ORDERLY: Ah, he used to be a gangster.
Name's Gilzean. Maybe Gold?
He took a slug in the noodle.
Been in a coma six months.
So, hospital brass
wants to free up beds?
Yeah. Say take him upstate.
(BOTH LAUGHING RAUCOUSLY)
Rest in Peace, Butch
Gilzean, Cyrus Gold,
(CHUCKLES) whoever
the hell you are.
(BOTH LAUGHING RAUCOUSLY)
Hey, Harvey, has anyone
contacted you about Ra's al Ghul?
No.
I just heard from
Judge Bam Bam's clerk.
- His trial got pushed off the docket.
- And?
And I want to make sure, him
being minister of a foreign country,
doesn't let him
weasel out of this.
- He killed the boy.
- That's above my pay grade, pal.
I just bust the bad guys.
Do you?
These are release forms.
Of my collars.
Let me guess, each one of them
has a license from Penguin, right?
Jim, I am stuck between
a rock and a hard place.
Every moop you
bust with a license,
the Commissioner
orders me to let him go.
What am I supposed to do?
- Your job.
- I am doing my job.
Gordon, got a call
from the judge's clerk.
It's about Ra's al Ghul.
- Here.
- I'm doing my job.
Master Bruce.
No sleep?
Again?
Once more about
that boy's death.
Don't say it's not my fault.
It is my fault.
- Alex is dead because I hesitated.
- Well, perhaps you did,
but that doesn't make
you his murderer, does it?
Ra's killed that innocent little
boy and he's going to pay for it.
You really think locking him
up in Blackgate will stop him?
He still wants his dagger.
Stop going on about the
bloody dagger, will you?
Just so we can just get
some breakfast. Please.
I think I finally found something
in Dr. Winthrop's notes.
There's a description
on the handle
that Dr. Winthrop
was able to decipher.
Says the knife is
intended for the one
who was bathed in
the healing waters.
Right. Well, assuming that's not
me, that would be our boy Ra's.
But that doesn't have to
mean it's for him to use.
Perhaps to be used against him.
- I see.
- No.
You clearly don't.
What you're suggesting is
that knife and that knife alone
is the only thing
capable of doing him in.
If Ra's al Ghul believes
this knife will kill him,
that could explain
why he wants it so bad.
So he can destroy it.
Before someone
fulfills the prophecy.
Master Bruce, I know that you
feel bad about Alex, we all do.
But at this point, you
must remember your vow.
No killing.
Taking a life, never
mind how justified,
will lead you down a darker path
than you could ever possibly imagine.
I know. I've been down it.
- Do you understand me, Master Bruce?
- I understand.
Good.
Just get yourself ready.
Chop-chop.
WOMAN: Such a tragedy.
He was only a child,
and always so lovely.
A heinous crime,
perpetrated against
such an innocent boy.
WOMAN: And his grandfather,
murdered, just the day before.
I'll just be a moment,
Master Bruce.
Diplomatic immunity.
You are joking, ain't you?
The Nanda Parbat embassy
filed papers to have him extradited.
- Could happen this week.
- The monster killed a child.
I know. I was there. Look,
I'm telling this
you as a courtesy.
- Oh!
- But the news will get out.
When it does, I need
you to watch Bruce.
I'm worried about him.
And you blame me?
(SIGHS)
You're his guardian, aren't you?
You're supposed to protect him,
and instead you've been
placing him in harm's way.
ALFRED: Oh, I see.
So that's rankles, is it?
Keeping you in the dark?
Well, if I was you, I'd focus
on your own job, Detective,
which is keeping Ra's al
Ghul behind bars, tucked up.
Just keep the news away
from Bruce as long as you can.
On that, we agree, Detective.
The boy's been through enough.
(RACY INSTRUMENTAL
MUSIC PLAYING)
(LOCKER DOOR OPENING)
(GATE BUZZING)
Thanks for coming, Barbara.
Hell of a chicken coop.
So what's the angle?
How about this?
Say the word, we'll be home,
drinking Chianti by dinnertime.
I think I'll decline.
So why did you call me here?
To say goodbye.
When I brought you back to life,
I asked you to be my
eyes and ears in Gotham.
- You became so much more.
- Save it.
What about everything
you promised me?
Do as I ask, and I will give
you a gift beyond your imagining.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
What the hell was that?
You will see.
Goodbye, Barbara.
(DOOR SHUTS)
(OMINOUS INSTRUMENTAL
MUSIC PLAYING)
(GRUNTING)
(SINGING) Born on a Monday
Christened on Tuesday
Married on a Wednesday
Took ill on Thursday
Grew worse on Friday
Died on Saturday
Buried on...
Sweet mother of Mary.
Never seen nothing
like him before.
He's white as a picket fence.
Easy. We ain't gonna hurt you.
What happened to
your drawers, big fella?
(SQUEALS)
Easy.
No!
(GRUNTING)
We're gonna get you, you freak.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(GASPING) Who are you?
("SOLOMON GRUNDY" PLAYING)
"Solomon Grundy.
"Born...
on Monday."
License compliance amongst
the GCPD remains high.
The program is an
unmitigated success.
Numbers, Mr. Penn.
According to my tabulations,
86 percent of crime is
accounted for under Pax Penguina.
Which means that 14
percent of crime happens
outside of my licensing system.
The numbers are very
good, Mr. Cobblepot.
Get Firefly. I want
examples made.
Yes, that might help.
But then, if scorching a
few idiots was all it took,
anyone could rule Gotham.
Thank you for your
insight, Miss Falcone.
I don't recall summoning you.
I came to see if you had
lunch plans tomorrow.
An invitation?
(SCOFFS)
After I killed your father's
last remaining loyalists?
(CHUCKLES)
Perhaps you overestimate
the pleasure of your company.
Oswald.
You may think
you have everything
but there is one
thing you don't have.
The Falcone name.
A name that once accounted
for all criminal activity in Gotham.
As in, one hundred percent.
Now you're just rubbing it in.
I propose we have
lunch somewhere public.
By doing so, you'll show Gotham
that you have the support
of the Falcone family.
And that should be enough
to send those outlying
criminal elements
scurrying back
under your umbrella.
Mr. Penn, item number
four on my to-do list.
Kill Sofia Falcone.
Add a question mark, will you?
Tomorrow it is.
God! Your people
have pills for everything!
Insomnia. Anxiety. You have
to have something for me.
I don't know. A pill
to reverse the effect
of having your brain
frozen and unfrozen?
That's kind of specific.
I will not be condescended
to by an idiot in a lab coat!
You're not even a doctor!
Okay, relax, man. Just
tell me your symptoms.
Fogginess of the mind,
decreased capacity to
think ten steps ahead,
inability to solve riddles.
I have got to improve
my brain function.
I could take a
pill or a vitamin.
I'll even consider
a natural remedy.
I don't want to get your hopes
up, but there is something.
What? Tell me.
A trial drug.
It claims to boost your
natural cognitive abilities.
- That's perfect! Where is this?
- The sample drawer.
- What is it called?
- Smartivia.
Blue pills. Diamond shaped.
Smartivia. Smartivia.
I don't see them.
Try towards the back.
Ah! I don't see it.
Here it is.
(GROANING)
A fake gun? Seriously?
Wait, wait, wait. I
just need to know.
Do these work?
No, dummy. They're sugar pills.
And I'm calling the police.
(ALARM RINGING IN DISTANCE)
Go on, gently.
(GASPING)
(SIRENS BLARING)
(GROWLS)
Ow! (PANTING)
(YELLS)
Butch!
You know Grundy?
Butch.
I have never had
an issue with you.
Barbara Kean, she's the problem.
You and Tabitha were
innocent bystanders.
Wow. You don't get
much sun. Look...
Man talk too much.
- Collins. Deal with this, will you?
- Yep.
Gordon. Gordon!
- Bruce is gone.
- What?
- You've got to get me into Blackgate.
- What are you talking about?
When we got back from the wake,
he said he was gonna
go straight to bed,
but he must have snuck
out between then and now.
My concern is that
he's taken the knife...
and he's gonna try
and kill Ra's al Ghul.
- You're serious?
- He's being bloody serious.
We gotta go to Blackgate now.
And then you can
tell me the many ways
I failed the child, all right?
- Oh, I will.
- Listen to me.
The boy is on the verge
of doing something that
there's no coming back from.
He needs our help.
All right.
Let's go.
(DOGS BARKING)
(TENSE INSTRUMENTAL
MUSIC PLAYING)
It's about time. Shift
ended five minutes ago.
Come on.
(ENTHRALLING
INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC PLAYING)
You weak,
foolish boy.
(GRUNTS)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(GASPING)
You're still not ready.
My name is Bruce
Wayne. Stop him!
Stop him!
Master al Ghul.
Take him below.
What... what are you doing?
(DOOR BUZZING)
We got your call,
but I checked the logs.
Bruce Wayne hasn't been here.
With all due respect, I don't
think he'd come as a regular visitor.
He's a billionaire, after all.
I think what Mr. Pennyworth
is trying to say
is Bruce Wayne could have
paid someone to get him in here.
No offense.
We just want to look around.
Sure. Whatever you want.
But you came all the
way here for nothing.
And we're gonna
need your weapons.
Standard procedure.
Of course.
(CLEARS THROAT)
- Finished?
- That's absolutely it.
Unless you wanna
check my undercrackers.
This way.
Undercrackers?
They're here.
(GROANING)
Sugar pills, my foot.
That dream was horrible.
Oh, my God! Oh, you're real.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
You know Grundy?
What? No. No.
No, who's Grundy?
Solomon Grundy.
Born on Monday.
Your hand. How...
I'm sorry, what happened to you?
Grundy not know.
Okay, let me get this
straight. You don't remember...
who you are or how you got here?
I'm sorry.
Grundy, I don't know you.
Best of luck, though.
Hope you get the skin
thing figured out. Later.
(SCREAMING)
You know Grundy.
You help Grundy.
Be Grundy friend.
I'm attempting to be civil.
But I can't help you.
Why?
I just can't. All right?
- Why?
- Because...
- Because I can't even help myself.
Ow!
You don't know who you
are. Well, that makes two of us.
I used to be smart.
Brilliant.
And now that's gone.
I can't even rob a pharmacy.
So you want me to help you?
I can't.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Well, I am feeling
a bit peckish.
We are closed.
Janos.
Last I saw you was
at my tenth birthday.
You bought me ruby earrings.
Said it would be a fitting gift
for the daughter of
the king of Gotham.
Sofia Falcone.
I heard you had
returned to Gotham.
What can I do for you?
I was wondering how you
were faring under Penguin's rule.
The Szabo family
is quite content
under Oswald Cobblepot's
licensing system.
But even if we were not,
we would be wise
enough to not say anything.
Good.
Because I've invited him
to your restaurant for lunch.
And I want it to be a
lunch he'll never forget.
(FUNKY INSTRUMENTAL
MUSIC PLAYING)
RA'S: Bruce...
Where am I?
Beneath Blackgate Penitentiary.
Alfred Pennyworth and
Jim Gordon are upstairs.
In the company, unbeknownst
to them, of my men.
Let them go. They have
nothing to do with this.
Still playing the
white knight, Bruce?
You replaced the
guards before I got here.
I'm sure your friends
can fend for themselves.
You applied for diplomatic
immunity, knowing I'd hear about it.
And come for you.
I wanted the knife.
But not for the
reason you think.
It's been ages since I
first held this dagger.
It was given to me
moments after I was bathed
in the Lazarus Pit.
Submerged in the waters.
(GASPING)
Suspended between
life and death.
I saw a vision of you,
my heir.
You're insane.
I'm not your heir. I
don't even understand
what that means.
It means that you
are the only one
who can end my suffering.
Please.
You want me to kill you?
Set me free.
Well, thanks for
the snack, big guy.
But it's been an emotional day.
Gotta go.
(EXCLAIMS)
Not this again, come on!
I've told you, I'm
better off on my own
and you are, too.
So let go!
Let go!
Hey, freak.
I knew we'd find you.
And it looks like
you got a friend.
I assure you, we
are not friends.
Get 'em. Both of 'em.
No, no!
(GRUNTING AND GROANING)
Grundy!
(SCREAMING)
Hot! Hot!
Grundy friend, help!
Don't leave. No. Help!
Help. Hot. Hot!
Hot!
(GROANING)
Grundy friend not dumb.
Grundy friend...
smart.
Oh, yes.
Yeah, you're right.
Water beats fire. (LAUGHS)
That was smart.
Oh, boy.
(GASPING) I can't breathe.
Oswald.
- They said this is their best table.
- Interesting choice.
Are you sure it's
not too intimate?
The point was to get the word
out that the Falcones support me.
Don't worry. People will talk.
I chose this place because I
heard your mother is Hungarian.
I thought you might
like a taste of home.
(SCOFFS)
I can assure you, Oswald,
I'm not here to poison you.
Perhaps.
(COUGHS)
Well, the chef likes to go
heavy on the paprika, doesn't he?
How is the food otherwise?
Serviceable.
Well, I'm stuffed. Thank you so
much for meeting me, Miss Falcone.
And thank you to your
family for their support.
You can't leave until
you've tried the goulash.
If it's anything like the
chicken paprika, I'll pass.
It's a house specialty.
My mother made goulash.
Brought the recipe
from Budapest.
Handed down through
her family for 300 years.
I doubt this will hold a candle.
(GRUNTS)
- I'm leaving.
- Oswald.
Oswald!
It took me forever to
find his mother's recipe.
Did you follow it exactly?
I followed the recipe to a T.
The little man didn't like?
Honestly, I don't know.
How long have you worked here?
Two years, thereabouts.
I was in Blackgate for a time.
- We must not have overlapped.
- Yeah?
- As a guard?
- As a prisoner.
Oh, yeah.
Heard about that.
Is there a reason why you're not
taking us through maximum security?
Prisoners are in the
yard this time of day.
Been some changes
since you were here.
McCloskey? That's funny.
I know another J.
McCloskey who works here.
My cousin. Gets
confusing sometimes.
All right. Let's go,
through this door.
I've got to say, mate, I really love
what you've done with the old place.
However, I've got
a question for you.
Yeah?
Where are the real guards?
(ALL GRUNTING AND GROANING)
Where is Bruce Wayne?
- Ra's al Ghul has plans for the boy.
- Where is he?
(CHUCKLES)
You'll never find him.
Oh, you underestimate
my resolve, pal.
Well, at least we
know Bruce is here.
Well, we've walked the
floor. Where could he be?
There's the yard.
The tower, but
they're too public.
There's a sub-basement.
Accessible by the service elevator.
Which way?
(DOOR OPENS)
God.
Who did I tell you,
specifically, not to let in here?
Miss Falcone is
here to see you, sir.
I'm sorry, Oswald. I'm not
sure what upset you, but...
Enough!
Did you think I would really believe
this was all some coincidence?
That goulash tasted exactly
like my mother used to make.
You can't fault me for the
restaurant's authenticity.
You're buttering me up.
But for what?
Is it so hard to believe that
someone would want to
do something nice for you?
There was only one
person in my whole life
who ever did things for me
without wanting something in return.
And that was my mother.
Then I envy you.
My father never helped
anyone unless it benefited him.
And eventually, it drove
away everyone who loved him.
Go. I'll decide what
to do with you later.
- Oswald, I only want to help you.
- Oh, you wanna help?
Try leaving.
(SCOFFS)
Your foot.
It's just the weather.
(BREATHING SHAKILY)
What are you doing?
- Don't.
- (SOFTLY) It's okay.
And I won't judge.
When I was a child, I broke my
ankle while playing with my cousins.
I was desperate. Crying in pain.
My father told
me to put ice on it.
Toughen up, stop with the tears.
But my mother went
with me to the hospital.
And on the way, she told me
that cold actually
increases the pain.
What's needed is warmth.
My mother.
She used to sing.
(HUMMING)
RA'S: This may be hard
for you to understand.
But I have walked this
earth for centuries...
waiting for you, Bruce.
Only you can kill me,
and only with that dagger.
That is my curse.
That is the meaning
of my vision.
I don't believe you.
- Believe me.
- This is just another manipulation.
See.
Look.
My true form.
Every moment
of my life is agony.
End my suffering.
Whatever your curse is,
you deserve it for
what you've done.
You're angry,
Bruce. I understand.
But unless you strike me down
with that blade, you
will never be free.
No!
I won't.
Then allow me to tell
you what will happen...
if you don't kill me.
I will disappear.
And let you live your life.
You will follow
the path of light.
Grow into a fine man.
Become a husband.
A father.
There may be a
day when you forget
I ever existed.
But then, I will return.
And I will kill
everyone you love.
Just as you watched
your parents die.
Just as you watched me
slice your friend's throat,
I will slaughter your wife and
children before your very eyes
and there will be nothing
you can do about it.
(GRUNTING AND GASPING)
Die.
(SCREAMING)
Yes. (BREATHING HEAVILY)
(INDISTINCT ANNOUNCEMENTS)
Are you going to arrest me?
For what?
For murder.
I don't know what
I just saw in there.
But as far as I'm concerned,
Ra's al Ghul's men broke
into Blackgate and he escaped.
I betrayed myself, and
my parents' memory.
I took a life.
I did exactly what
Ra's said I would.
Just because you know you're
capable of doing something
doesn't mean it
has to happen again.
Bruce, you and I have
known each other a long time.
Since the night your
parents were murdered.
Now you may not feel
like you're that kid anymore,
but I know that you are.
One who believes in doing good,
and fighting for what's right,
who will do anything to
keep the people he loves safe.
Nothing that happened
today changes that.
What are you doing?
You said it yourself.
It's over.
No.
- Can't let you do that, Master Bruce.
- Alfred.
Listen, we started
this vigilante caper
to prepare for Ra's
return, didn't we?
It's become so
much bigger than that.
I see that now, I mean, I
was wrong and you were right.
You can make a difference.
I'm not the hero Gotham needs.
I made that decision the
moment I killed Ra's al Ghul.
I took the dark path.
Yes, you did.
And it's gonna be a
long, bumpy journey back.
But I believe in you, Master Bruce.
I always have and I... I always will.
And I understand that
you don't feel worthy now.
But when you do, this...
this will be waiting for you.
As will I, sir.
These guys that attacked us,
they didn't even have
five bucks between them.
We need a new plan.
What?
Truth.
Grundy friend know...
Grundy?
You deserve to know...
you and I,
(SIGHS)
were the very best of friends.
And then something
happened to you
and I just didn't recognize you.
But what is important is
that with your muscles,
we can make money.
And with money, we
can make me smart again.
And then we'll figure out
what happened to you.
Just trust me, okay?
Grundy, come on.
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING)
(PEOPLE CHATTERING AND CHEERING)
(PUNCHES THUMPING)
(GRUNTING)
Yeah, come on!
What is this? A knitting
circle? Let's see some blood!
Hey, I'm looking for the
person in charge here.
You're looking at her.
What do you want, squirt?
Well, if there's money to be had,
we'd like to put our hat in the ring.
(LAUGHS SARCASTICALLY)
And who are you?
I'm... Hey!
Come back.
I'm this fine
gentleman's manager.
Trust me, he's a monster.
Well, more grist for the mill.
We'll get you patched
up. Then we'll talk.
Hey!
Go get the doc.
All right. One, two, three.
Hey, doc! Cherry wants you
to come look at some new guy.
WOMAN: I'll be right there.
English - SDH